Guide to the City Club of New York Records 1890-1978 MS 116
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Bound Minutes Books, 1892-1894, 1904-1943; 12 Linear feet
  - Minutes of the Membership Commmittee, 1929-1932 (Offsite-box CC-10, Volume 39)
  - Minutes of the City Affairs Committee, 1914-1915 (Offsite-box CC-10, Volume 40)
    Includes correspondence regarding city affairs. Topics include: hospitals, electric signs, heights of buildings, copy of municipal financing address from Edmund Fisher, vault rentals, speed regulations, proposal of long term budget for New York City, Court House site, water supply, and telephone franchises.
  - Minutes of the Legislation Committee, 1905-1907 (Offsite-box CC-10, Volume 41)
  - Minutes of the Legislation Committee, 1909-1914 (Offsite-box CC-11, Volume 42)
  - Minutes of the Legislation Committee, 1915-1919 (Offsite-box CC-11, Volume 43)
  - Minutes of the Legislation Committee, 1920-1930 (Offsite-box CC-11, Volume 44)
  - Minutes of the Legislation Committee, 1931-1936 (Offsite-box CC-11, Volume 45)
  - Minutes of the House Committee, 1892-1894 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 9)
    Includes House Rules and furnishings of the Clubhouse.
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, 1904-1907 (Offsite-box CC-12, Volume 46)
    Includes foldout of Hotel Astor Banquet floor diagram and diagrams of Grand Ball room, and materials from the Special Committee on the financial condition of the club.
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, A-C, 1908-1913 (Offsite-box CC-12, Volume 47)
    Includes report on stage coach companies and Fifth Avenue Transportation company route map of Manhattan (1913).
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, D-Po, 1908-1913 (Offsite-box CC-12, Volume 48)
    Includes minutes of Committee on "Negro Problem" discussing the need to investigate safe and sanitary housing conditions for African Americans in Harlem, and minutes from Fire Protection committee.
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, Pu-Z, 1908-1913 (Offsite-box CC-12, Volume 49)
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, 1914 (Offsite-box CC-13, Volume 50)
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, 1915 (Offsite-box CC-13, Volume 51)
    Includes minutes and materials from Committees on Labor Problems, Correctional Institutions, and Pending Amendments to the Constitution. Documents found loose in the volume were removed to the following folder.
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, Courts, 1915 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 10)
    Loose materials from Volume 51 - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees.
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, A-C, 1916-1917 (Offsite-box CC-13, Volume 52)
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, D-M, 1916-1917 (Offsite-box CC-13, Volume 53)
    Includes House minutes and correspondence protesting women smoking inside the Club House, and minutes from the Committee on Immigration.
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, N-W, 1916-1917 (Offsite-box CC-13, Volume 54)
    Includes minutes from Committee on Nuisances, Pensions, and the Special Committee on State Farm Colony for Vagrants.
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, A-D, 1918 (Offsite-box CC-14, Volume 55)
    Includes sub-committee on advertising in subways.
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, E-Z, 1918 (Offsite-box CC-14, Volume 56)
    Includes materials from committees on Employment Exchanges, and Industrial Relations and Reconstruction.
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, 1919 (Offsite-box CC-14, Volume 57)
    Includes State Retrenchment and Reorganization Committee, and House Committee minutes regarding proposal for no smoking during lectures when women are present.
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, 1920-1921 (Offsite-box CC-14, Volume 58)
    Includes minutes of the Committee on Automobile Accidents and the Committee on Restoration of City Hall Park.
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, 1922-1924 (Offsite-box CC-15, Volume 59)
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, 1925-1927 (Offsite-box CC-15, Volume 60)
    Includes minutes of several special committees: Special Committee on Constitutional Amendments, Special Committee on Crime Problem, Special Committee on New Club House, and Special Commitee on Use of Public School Buildings.
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, 1928-1930 (Offsite-box CC-15, Volume 61)
    Includes materials from the Special Committee appointed to report with regard to Communist Meetings, Special Committee on Suburban Affairs, and sub-committees of the City Committee including: City Departments, Markets, Taxation and Budget. Documents found loose in the volume were removed to the following folder.
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, 1928-1930 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 11)
    Includes the loose materials from volume 61, Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees (1928-1930).
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, 1931-1932 (Offsite-box CC-15, Volume 62)
    Includes materials from the sub-committee on Housing and Height of Buildings, and Special Committee on Magistrates' Courts.
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, 1933-1935 (Offsite-box CC-16, Volume 63)
    Includes Parks Committee minutes regarding the Moses Bill to centralize the Park Department and allow Robert Moses to maintain his position, and minutes regarding proposed redesign of Washington Square Park.
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, A-L (3 folders), 1936 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 12-14)
    Materials were removed from original binder. Includes sub-committees on Port Commerce, Public Utilities, Social Welfare, and minutes from a lecture from the Crime Prevention Committee discussion of sterilization as a form of crime prevention.
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees, M-Z, 1936 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1)
  - Minutes of Miscellaneous Committees (3 folders), 1938-1940 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2-4)
    Includes materials regarding proposed Brooklyn Battery Bridge/Tunnel, the proposed redesign of Washington Square Park, dog control in the city, and materials from the sub-committee on regulations for neon signs.
  - Minutes of Various Committees (4 folders), 1936-1938 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 5-8)
    Includes materials from sub-committees on Public Relief, Narcotics, and the World's Fair, and minutes from the Constitutional Convention Committee and Aviation Committee.
- Series II. Records and Correspondence Files, 1890s-1957; 4.75 Linear feet
  This series includes all records and correspondence of City Club, primarily from 1930-1957. These materials include minutes from the Board of Trustees and Committees past the years of the bound volumes of Series I, correspondence, materials from events, pamphlets, reports, City Club Bulletins, news clippings, and all membership materials from this period. Included are reports and materials related to various civic issues in New York City and petitions to legislators. These topics include voting recommendations, subway fare raises, transit strikes, trials, housing, civil defense, education, and municipal affairs.
  The materials in the series have been organized into seven subseries according to the contents of the files and original boxes.
  Subseries II.A. Trustee and Executive Committee Files
  Subseries II.B. General Correspondence
  Subseries II.C. Committees
  Subseries II.D. Events
  Subseries II.E. Club History
  Subseries II.F. Bulletins
  Subseries II.G. Miscellaneous
  The original order of materials within folders has been retained, much of which is reverse chronological order. The folders were primarily in somewhat alphabetical order with some chronological order of groupings, with separate boxes for Board of Trustees materials and miscellaneous files. All files are now arranged according to their contents, with some folders condensed and labeled as such. The original separation of Trustee materials and miscellaneous files was retained through Subseries II.A. Trustee and Executive Committee Files and Subseries II.G. Miscellaneous.
  - Subseries II.A. Trustee and Executive Committee Files, 1930-1953; 1 Linear feet
    The materials in this subseries are the minutes and materials of the Board of Trustees and Executive committee including correspondence, reports, financial information, and several miscellaneous files related to civic issues including voting information, education, and plans to redevelop Washington Square Park.
    The materials are arranged in chronological order within subject groupings including minutes, Treasurer's documents, and individual's files. The contents of folders are in their original order which is primarily reverse chronological, and some folders were condensed to include related material.
    - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1941-1943 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1943-1944 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Women's City Club of New York, 1941-1942 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
      Includes financials, correspondence, and minutes related to Women's City Club and shared spaces of the Clubs.
    - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1945 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
      Includes minutes and condolence letter to Eleanor Roosevelt regarding FDR's passing and membership.
    - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1946 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Resolution - Judges have Lawyers for Secretaries, 1946 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1947-1949 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Minutes of the Board of Trustees (2 Folders), 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9-10)
      Includes plan to dissolve City Club and subsequent reorganization plan.
    - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1952 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1953 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    - General Folder Trustee Transfer File, 1947-1949 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
      Includes Trustee rosters and correspondence.
    - Voting Information Schedule 1, 1947 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
      Includes Club Bulletin and press release with voting recommendations for amendments and propositions.
    - Board of Trustee notices, 1951-1953 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    - Trustees Miscellaneous, 1941-1942 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
      Includes correspondence, notices, and minutes.
    - Tax Information, 1913-1942 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
    - Sugar Rationing, 1941-1942 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
    - Finances, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
    - Treasurer Receipted Bills, Dues Letters to Members, Dues Contribution Lists (2 Folders), 1950-1953 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20-21)
    - Treasurer's Reports, 1945-1949 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - House Budgets, 1941-1943 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23)
    - Petty Cash, 1950-1953 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 25)
    - Washington Square Materials, 1939 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 26)
      Includes memo, correspondence with Robert Moses, and proposed plans for remodeling of Washington Square Park.
    - U.S. Office of Education, 1930-1941 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 27)
      Includes correspondence and publications from Office of Education.
    - Executive Committee, 1945-1951 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 28)
      Includes minutes and correspondence.
    - Howard C. Kelly President, 1942 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 29)
      Includes correspondence and memorandum.
    - Office Secretary, 1950 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 30)
    - Samuel H. Ordway, Jr. - President, 1951 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 31)
      Includes bill and correspondence.
    - Extra Sheets and Proof for Bulletin, 1947 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 32)
    - President's Letters to Members, 1951-1953 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 33)
    - Tax Reports, State Sales Tax, Gift Tax information Returns, 1933-1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 24)
  - Subseries II.B. General Correspondence, 1945-1952; 1 Linear feet
    The materials in this subseries are all of the general correspondence files of the City Club from 1945 to 1953. These materials include letters regarding requests for information, invitations, meeting notifications, membership dues letters, advertisements, and condolences.
    General correspondence is in its original order within each folder in reverse chronological order. The files were arranged in chronological order within this subseries.
    - General Correspondence (3 folders), 1945 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1-3)
    - General Correspondence (4 folders), 1946 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4-7)
      Includes letters to Joseph Addinizio regarding legislative representation for City Club.
    - General Correspondence (4 folders), 1947 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8-11)
      Includes letters regarding plans for rezoning the neighborhood of the United Nations (February 1947), 2 letters in German (September 1947).
    - General Correspondence (4 folders), January 1948- November 1948 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12-15)
    - General Correspondence (2 folders), December 1948-1949 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16-17)
      Includes discussion of consolidation of City Club with Citizens Union (May 1949), payment to Joseph Addinizio, and petitions to preserve Castle Clinton.
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1950-1952 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
  - Subseries II.C. Committees, 1937-1954; 1.5 Linear feet
    This subseries includes the minutes and correspondence of various City Club committees which were not bound. These materials include general committee rosters, correspondence, copies of reports and memorandums, and membership information.
    The folders were arranged according to committee in chronological order, and the contents of folders are in their original order.
    - City Club Committees, 1950-1954 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
      Includes Committee rosters, correspondence to members, membership blank, membership procedures.
    - Committee Preferences, 1950-1953 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
    - Committee Appointments and Committee Meetings, 1950-1953 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
      Includes Committee Appointment Letters, Committee rosters, notices of committee meetings, and committee report blank.
    - Awards Committee and Forbes Luncheon, 1937-1945 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
      Includes awards protocol, correspondence, recipient information, and invitations.
    - Special Committee to Revise By-laws and Constitution, 1950-1951 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
    - City Affairs Committee, 1936-1947 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
      Includes minutes, correspondence, Report of Courts Committee (1935 and 1938), and reports on the New York City Transit System and the Necessity for an Increased Fare.
    - City Affairs Committee (2 folders), 1951-1953 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7-8)
      Includes press releases, Municipal affairs committee minutes, and act to establish a Waterfront Commission of New York Harbor.
    - City Planning Commission, 1948-1949 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
      Includes City Affairs Committee materials, and Board of Transportation News (1948-1949).
    - Special Committee on Civil Defense Against Atomic Attack, 1950-1951 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
    - Legislative Correspondence, 1945 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
      Includes proposed amendments stamped Joseph F. Addinizio and Proposed rules for State Commission Against Discrimination.
    - Correspondence - Legislation, 1947 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
    - Committee on Legislation (3 folders), 1946-1948 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13-15)
      Includes proposed amendments January 8-9th, 1947 and State Legislature Bulletins 1947.
    - Letter and Weis Legislation Committee Report, 1947 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 16)
    - Calendars, 1946-1949 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17)
      Includes current and deferred legislative calendars.
    - Assembly Bills on the Calendar, 1947 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 18)
    - Assembly Bills not on the Calendar, 1947 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 19)
    - Legislation Committee, 1949-1953 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 20-21)
      Includes special calendars, rosters, and correspondence.
    - Court Clerk Salaries - Study by Edward Goodell, January 1941 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 22)
    - Citizens' Union, 1951 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 23)
      Includes report and materials from Citizens' Union.
    - Special Committee on Police Reporting Procedures, 1950-1951 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 24)
      Includes correspondence, statistics, remarks by Allen Will Harris, and reports.
    - Committee on Law Enforcement, 1950-1951 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 25)
    - General Membership Figures, 1941-1943 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
      Includes membership income, rosters, and invitations.
    - Membership and Resignations, 1943 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
      Includes correspondence, rosters, and membership changes.
    - Annual Meeting Membership Folder, 1945-1947 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
    - Membership Meetings, 1950-1953 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
      Includes correspondence with speakers and invitations to lectures.
    - Membership Figures, February 1945-February 1947 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
    - Report to Membership, June 1949-October 1949 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
      Includes Letter to Membership Luncheon October 4.
    - Prospective Membership and Rejected Membership Applications, 1950-1951 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7)
    - Membership Rosters, 1947-1949 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8)
    - Membership - General, 1949-1951 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9)
      Includes letters to membership, correspondence, rosters, and potential new member pages.
    - Copies of Weis' Reports Paid Membership, 1947-1950 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 10)
      Includes daily club receipts and summaries.
    - Military Absentee Letter, February 1946 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 11)
    - Membership Material, 1948-1949 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12)
      Includes rosters and daily receipts.
    - Nominating Committee, 1941-1953 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 13)
      Includes correspondence and election nominations for Board of Trustees.
    - Letters to Members, 1945-1953 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 14)
      Includes nomination letters, Action on Election Ballot Amendments and Proposal #1, and City Club updates.
    - Special Committee on Increase of Membership, 1950-1953 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 15)
      Includes Membership Drive April 1953 Mr. Seeler materials, Membership Drive 1952 Mr. Cook materials, and correspondence.
    - Committee on Transportation and Traffic, 1950-1952 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 16)
    - Program Committee, 1951-1953 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 17)
    - Speakers, 1951 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 18)
      Includes correspondence and text of addresses from speakers.
    - Special Meetings, 1950 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 19)
      Includes invitations for special meeting with Citizens' Union.
    - Form Letters, 1940-1941 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 20)
  - Subseries II.D. Events, 1941-1952; 0.5 Linear feet
    The materials in this subseries are all related to large scale events held by City Club including anniversaries, lectures, and conferences. These materials include invitations, correspondence, attendee lists, response cards, and several photographs.
    Materials in this subseries are arranged chronological by event with the exception of the Lecture Series folder that spans multiple years, and the original order of the materials within each file has been retained.
    - Hospital Presidents V Plan Conference (2 folders), 1941 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 21-22)
      Includes materials from conference and City Club's proposed medical plan for New York City.
    - 50th Anniversary, 1942 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 23)
      Includes newsclippings regarding traffic patterns.
    - Club Luncheon, 1946-1947 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 24)
      Includes materials from luncheons: November 18, 1946, January 29, 1947, and postponed April 19.
    - Hosts for Club on Tuesdays, 1950 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 25)
    - 60th Anniversary Dinner Mr. Samuel H. Ordway Jr., 1952 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 26)
    - 60th Anniversary, 1952-1955 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 27)
      Includes photographs from Anniversary dinner, membership kit letters, and A Practical Program for Replanning the City of New York (1955).
    - Response Cards, 1952 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 28)
    - Lecture Series, 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 4, Folder 29)
  - Subseries II.E. Club History, 1890s-1951; 0.25 Linear feet
    This subseries includes materials related to the history of City Club and its locations, including inventories of furniture and materials, correspondence, pamphlets and booklets, bills, and liquor licenses.
    The folders in this subseries are arranged in primarily chronological order, with the original order of materials within the folder.
    - History of City Club, 1890s-1940s (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
      Includes pamphlets, Board of Trustees records, Harper's Weekly (1895), and handbook list of members.
    - Liquor Information, 1933-1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
      Includes liquor licenses for Club dining room, and liquor inventory.
    - Organizations Solicited for City Club Dining Room, 1940 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
      Includes correspondence regarding pictures loaned for the dining room.
    - Reorganization of City Club (move) and Hotel Russel, 1944-1951 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
      Materials regarding the move to Hotel Russel.
    - Inventory - City Club, November 3, 1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
      Includes Inventory of Furniture and Furnishings at 55 West 44th Street.
  - Subseries II.F. Bulletins, 1938-1953; 0.25 Linear feet
    This subseries contains Bulletins and releases put out by City Club, and sample materials used for printing. This includes copies of the circularizing City Club Bulletin, materials regarding Michael Quill and the transit strike, and several press releases.
    The folders in the subseries are arranged primarily by their original order, though the publicity releases have been arranged in chronological order, as well as the City Club Bulletins. Several folders were condensed according to their contents and are labeled.
    - Printing Styles, 1950s (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
    - Ouster of Quill Letter to City, 1946 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
      Includes newsclippings and letter to city regarding Michael J. Quill and transportation strike.
    - Publicity Releases (2 folders), 1940-1953 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 8-9)
      Includes releases and The Press Speaks booklet on tax relief, release proposing mandatory car mufflers, voting, waterfront crime, and investigation of Mayor William O'Dwyer.
    - City Club Bulletins - Circularizing, 1938-1947 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10)
    - Bulletins - Sample Specimens, 1940s (Offsite-box 5, Folder 11)
    - Municipal Reference Library Notes, 1950s (Offsite-box 5, Folder 12)
  - Subseries II.G. Miscellaneous, 1943-1957; 0.25 Linear feet
    The folders and materials of the last subseries contain the miscellaneous and "to be filed" folders of the Records and Correspondence Files series. These materials have been kept in their original file order according to their groupings of To be Filed materials and miscellaneous materials. The folders contain minutes from the Board of Trustees and committees, correspondence, copies of invitations, press clippings, reports, photographs, stamps and materials regarding City Club's office relocation in 1954.
    The materials in this subseries retained their original order for files and the contents of each file.
    - Miscellaneous - To be Filed, 1954 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 13)
      Includes full text Report of the Sub-committee on Waterfront Crime of the Municipal Affairs Committee.
    - To be Filed, 1950-1954 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 14)
      Includes: photographs from 60th Anniversary Dinner, requests for information, address by Allen Will Harris, correspondence with the National Municipal League regarding City Club records given to New York Public Library, gift acknowledgement from New-York Historical Society for Anniversary Reports of Harvard College Classes, relocation and urban development, and correspondence.
    - To be Filed, 1953-1954 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 15)